<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consort of the creatures with the creator, and with themselues. By R.R. of Lincolnes Inne student in the common lawes.</title>
            <author>Rawlyns, Roger.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106595</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6953</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 737:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consort of the creatures with the creator, and with themselues. By R.R. of Lincolnes Inne student in the common lawes.</title>
                  <author>Rawlyns, Roger.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin, for William Young and Raph Iac-son [sic] ,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by STC to Roger Rawlyns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Man (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6953:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6953:1"/>
            <p>A Conſort of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and with <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By R. R. of <hi>Lincolnes Inne</hi> Student in the Common Lawes.</p>
            <q>
               <p>It is not good in all things and at all times to be aſhamed.</p>
               <bibl>Eccleſiaſt. 41.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>T O</head>
               <q>BY WISDOM PEACE BY PEACE PLENTY.</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> for <hi>William Young</hi> and <hi>Raph Iac-ſon.</hi> 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:6953:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Adam and Eve with the Tree, serpent, and other animals in the garden</figDesc>
                  <head>CHRISTVS <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <label> 1 <hi>Iah,</hi> or <hi>Iehouah,</hi>
                           </label> God.</item>
                        <item>2. Chriſt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>A</label> 
                           <label>3 <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus, vel</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</label> An Angel or a Man.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>I</label> 
                           <label>4 <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, vel Ratio,</hi>
                           </label> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>B</label> 
                           <label>5 <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
                           </label> a Brute thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>S</label> 
                           <label>6 <hi>Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi>
                           </label> Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>V</label> 
                           <label>7 <hi>Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi>
                           </label> A li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>V</label> 
                           <label>8 <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi>
                           </label> Life.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>H</label> 
                           <label>9 <hi>Homo,</hi>
                           </label> Man.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>10 <hi>Ratio,</hi>
                           </label> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="religious_treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6953:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Conſort of the Creatures,</hi> with the Creator, and with themſelues.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ECAVSE that I am to ſpeake of a Woord, which is conceaued by a ſound: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Word</hi> in Greek, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth aſwell <hi>Reaſon</hi> as <hi>Speach,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Speach</hi> is but a ſigne or note of thoſe things, which he that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, conceaueth in his minde, or Reaſon: and becauſe that Reaſon is occupied either about the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the will of the Creator, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their beings, their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ends. Firſt therefore, I think it good to ſpeake ſomewhat
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6953:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Sound, then next of a Word, then of this word <hi>Iehovah,</hi> then of God, after what manner hee is ſaid to be, then of Nature, or the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the Creatures, their beings, agreements, &amp; ends: and laſtly, how God is ſaid to be agreed with vs, &amp; to be our ende, according as may be gathered from this word &amp; figure.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sound.</head>
               <p>FIrſt therefore, as the word is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into the care by Sound: ſo doo the Creatures preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto the minde, by the eie, or Obſeruation, as in a continuall Harmonie, of their beings, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings: for, the Creatures haue (as in Muſicke) iarred, and oftentimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their courſes, for the benefite of the Children of God, as ſaith the Prophete <hi>Eſay, If thou goest through
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6953:3"/>the water, I wil be with thee, the ſtrong flouds ſhall not ouerwhelme thee, and if thou walkeſt through the fire, it ſhal not burne thee, and the flame ſhall not kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle vpon thee.</hi> So the Sunne and the Moone ſtood ſtill, at the beheaſt of <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> the Red Sea parted to make paſſage for the Children of <hi>Iſrael, Lots</hi> Wife was turned into a pillar of Salte, for a warning to vs, to flie too much care of worldlie things, Angles haue been conuerſant with men, <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe reprooued him riding to curſſe Gods people, the Viper did <hi>Paul</hi> no harme, the ſwift ſtreame of <hi>Iordane</hi> hath gone back, and the earth hath ſhaken; which cauſed the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration to ſay, <hi>Iuda was his Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, and Iſrael his dominion: The Sea ſaw that, and fled: Iordane was driuen backe: The Mountaines ſkipped like Rammes, and the little hilles like young
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6953:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sheepe: what ayled thee O thou Sea, that thou fleddest, &amp; thou Iordan that thou wast driuen backe? Yee Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines that ye skipped like Rammes, &amp; ye little hilles like young ſheepe? Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thou Earth at the preſence of the Lord, at the preſence of the God of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acob: which turned the hard Rock in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtanding water, and the flint ſtone into a ſpringing well.</hi> The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, mooued the Wiſeman to ſay, <hi>The Elements turned into them ſelues, like as when one tune is changed vpon an inſtrument of Muſicke, and yet all the reſidue keep their melodie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as an Harmonie to the Eare, is nothing but an agreement of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Sound, pleaſing the Senſe: ſo the Harmonie of the Creation, is a concurrence of continued Cauſes; than the conſideration whereof, no earthly thing can be by the eye more harmonious to the minde.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6953:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And as inarticulate Harmonie much delighteth the minde by Senſe: ſo woords Harmonious, which are conuerted with reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſideration, by the Senſe doo delight the minde of the Hearer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VVoord.</head>
               <p>AS by our Reaſon, thorough the helpe of Senſe, wee may knowe much; but yet to be wiſe to our ſelues onely, and to our onelie vſes; but by words wee communicate our knowledge and will to others: ſo doth God communicate his wil, and the knowledge of himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in Chriſt; who is called, <hi>The Word,</hi> as beeing the cauſe of the word of God, whereby hee is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6953:5"/>
               <head>Iehouah.</head>
               <p>THis is the great name of GOD, which he choſe after the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things: whereas, during the Creation, hee vſed <hi>Elohym;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, hee vſeth this name eleuen times in one chapter.</p>
               <p>This name was pronounced by the Sacrificer, in the bleſsing at the departure of the people from the Temple; &amp; otherwiſe was amongſt the Iewes ſignified by the name of 42. letters.</p>
               <p>If God gaue ſuch ſingular wit to <hi>Adam,</hi> to name euery beaſt ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, let vs then ſomewhat conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how greatly he wil be glorified in his owne name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6953:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of Being.</hi> How God will be ſaid to be, according to this word.</head>
               <p>FIrſt therefore, notwithſtanding that from this worde may bee drawne, the beings of Angells, of Men, of Beaſts, of Liuing things, &amp; ſo by ſound entendment of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, that belongeth vnto them, according to the end and order of the Creation, yet beſides, in this name are the ſignes of the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, of the time paſt, &amp; of the time to come; ſignifying, that, inaſmuch as that through him, euerie thing hath being, yet, he onely will bee ſaid to bee: for, Man, though he is, yet is the beſt man, but <hi>Abel,</hi> vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>Al is but moſt vaine vanitie</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>and all is moſt vanie</hi> (I ſay) <hi>and but plaine vanitie. The end,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6953:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>beſt of man, is <hi>to feare God, and to keepe his Commandements.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Man is ſaid to be in this word.</head>
               <p>BY the fiue vowells, which are in this word, is the being of Man inferred, becauſe that no word is without a vowell, no Propoſition or Speach without wordes, and Speach is conuerted with Reaſon, Reaſon being the eſſentiall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Chriſt is ſaid to be, according to this word.</head>
               <p>INaſmuch as in this word are ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified GOD and Man, is Chriſt both God and Man ſignified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6953:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>How the Angels are ſaid to be in this word.</head>
               <p>ANd for that that the Angells do partake with vs in vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, from the being of Man may alſo the being of the Angels be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred: for wee are ſaid to bee the moſt inferiour for vnderſtanding: that is, inferiour to the Angells in vnderſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a true Christian is in this Figure.</head>
               <p>NOw, hauing here found the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Man; let vs alſo ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to finde the beings of a true Chriſtian, of a bare Profeſſor, and of an Heathen man.</p>
               <p>Firſt therfore, that that that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath taught many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6953:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>much of the Creation, but not the knowledge &amp; acknowledgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in ſo great light as we behold him: therefore in this Figure haue we ſignified man below, according to his Reaſon, as in that place being the end of the Creation: but here in this figure we haue ſignified him next vnto Chriſt, according to the pure part of his minde, whereof himſelfe can giue no reaſon, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pure vnderſtanding: whereby wee are perſwaded, <hi>That neither death, neither life, neither An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, nor rule, neither power, neither things preſent, neither things to come, neither heigth, nor depth, neither any other creature ſhall ſeperate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſu our Lord.</hi> Which acknowledgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t belongeth to the whole Church, who notwithſtanding her blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, which in reaſon might make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6953:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>her vgly and loathſome, yet with comfort acknowlegeth her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the loue and grace of Chriſt, as noteth <hi>Salomon</hi> in that figuratiue ſpeach of the Church: <hi>I am blacke, (O ye daughters of Ieruſalem) but yet faire and wel fauoured, like as the tents of the Cedarenes, and as the hangings of Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a bare Profeſſor is in this Figure.</head>
               <p>INaſmuch as Reaſon is an <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence vpon a former Intelligence:</hi> and is the eſſence indifferently of al men good and bad: therefore may the wicked aſwell as the godly, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the written word, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the letter.</p>
               <p>But though the knowledge of Saluation, which is of Reaſon, may be learned indifferently, aſwell by the reprobate as the elect, out of the word of God, which is one ſubiect
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6953:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Reaſon, and may be bought for fee: yet this other acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is of pure vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is the immediate worke of God to the elect, which is not to be bought Sorcerer <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a Heathen man is in this Figure.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as from the bottome of this Figure, it ſeemeth that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reaſon vpwards by the Creature, lieth a way to the knowledge of the Creator, Reaſon being commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwell to the Heathen, as the falſe and true Chriſtian, let vs thereof a little conſider.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Heathen, wee reade, that the very Creature ſhall make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inexcuſable before God. Foraſmuch as that which may bee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6953:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>knowne of God, is manifeſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: God hauing ſhewed it vnto them; for the inuiſible things of him, that is, his eternall power and Godhead are ſeene by the Creation of the worlde, beeing conſidered in his works, to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they ſhould bee without excuſe, becauſe that when they knewe God, they glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him not as God, neither were thankful, but became vaine in their imaginations, and their fooliſh hart was full of darknes. And inaſmuch as a light ſeemeth to be giuen vnto the Heathen man out of this figure vnto Chriſt, let vs thereof ſoberly conſider. For, GOD in the whole courſe of the Creature, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined things of different qualitie by ſomewhat of a meane Nature: as in the combination of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of the bodies of Trees, of Beaſts, of Men: about whoſe brain
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6953:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>are two skinnes, that one called <hi>Pia Mater, Tender mother,</hi> for ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the braine; that other, <hi>Dura Mater, hard mother,</hi> for hardnes of the skull. Againe, betweene Senſe, and Reaſon are meanes, Common ſenſe, Imagination, and Memorie, of which againe Imagination is the meane, as waxe holding that, which for ſlipperines, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe cannot, and putting ouer to Memory the things ſo receiued. Againe, he ſeeing Plants to agree with beaſts in life, beaſts with men in ſenſe, ſhould now the naturall man, hauing thus farre followed the conduct of Nature, here ceaſe and finde no meane betweene God and Man? (for they aymed at the knowledge of God by thoſe terms of <hi>Cauſa cauſans, the cauſe cauſing,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Finis vltimus, the last end,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> according to this Figure,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6953:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Finis vltimus est, propter quem reli-reliqua deſiderantur, The laſt ende is that, for which all other things are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</hi>) Or rather ſeeking an Vnion to God, would not Reaſon lead him to the higheſt Creature in his knowledge, which was Man. Now, inaſmuch as the Philoſopher himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Omnia fiunt ad finem, All things are done for the end:</hi> What end more probable for him, who ſhould thus vnite the Godhead to the Manhood, than to agree Man with God? (as ſaith <hi>Amos</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>Two cannot walke together, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they bee agreed:</hi> And that they knewe ſinne and geſſed at a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſame, after this life to bee infliected, appeareth out of that of <hi>Tully,</hi> called <hi>Somnium Scipionis, Scipio his dream.</hi> The philoſopher is ſaid to haue cried out, <hi>ô ens entiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere mei: ô being of beings haue mercy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6953:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon me:</hi> which words, if a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould tranſlate, might he not ſay, <hi>O God in Chriſt looke vppon me:</hi> for that is to haue mercie? The three Wiſe men following the ſtarre, came from the Eaſt to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Chriſt: and it is ſaid, that a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher at the ſuffering of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior, ſeeing the Sunne darkened, &amp; the earth to quake, by obſeruation of Nature, cried out, <hi>Aut Deus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam patitur, aut totius orbis machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na deſtruetur, Either God ſuffereth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence in nature, or els the frame of the whole world ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Angels are ſaid to differ from Men.</head>
               <p>HAuing thus ſpoken ſomewhat of the agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Angels with Men, and of the agreement and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the pretending and true
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6953:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>chriſtian, &amp; likewiſe of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Heathen man: it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth good now in a word to ſpeak of the difference of men from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, which is this: that they by pure Intelligence do exerciſe their functions; but Man by Reaſon, which we haue termed, An Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence vpon Intelligence, becauſe that in Man, Vnderſtanding is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, by reaſon of the corruption of our firſt parents; by the vanitie of our mindes, by reaſon of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitie which our imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath with the Senſes; for the exceſſe of affections, for the exceſſe of touch, taſt, and exerciſe; for the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of humours, &amp; for the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of euill Spirits: for the relief of which infirmities, our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is helped by Reaſon, which is helped by Arte, either in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6953:11"/>queſtions, or els in the whole bodie of a Science, and Arte is the way to Argumentation, of which the firſt part proceedeth of <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, Intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> &amp; of Philoſophers is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of Longitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <hi>Maior.</hi> The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part is that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred of the firſt, &amp; is of Reaſon, of Philoſophers called <hi>Conſcientia, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> of Longitians <hi>Minior,</hi> which being wel inferred, the <hi>Maior</hi> muſt ſo cohere with it ſelfe, as they both may goe for graunted by the alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Anſwerer. The third part of Argumentation, or of a Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme, is of <hi>Intellectus,</hi> or of Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding now aſcertained by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> whereby wee knowe, that wee knowe the trueth, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Dictamen,</hi> of Logitians, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. Now Arte in the whole bodie of a Science, is nothing elſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6953:11"/>but a prudent collecting, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all ſuch Places, from which places, concerning anie queſtion in the whole bodie of that Science, may be vſed <hi>Argumentation:</hi> In e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery which Science, the Partes and Reaſons are finite, though of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall mixtures of the partes, may proceede Queſtions infinite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Beaſts and Vegetant or liuing things, haue their being, according to this Word.</head>
               <p>IN this word, are two <hi>Aſpirates,</hi> by which may be inferred the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of two ſenſible or breathing Creatures, that is, of Men, and of Beaſtes. And, for that nothing can breathe but liuing, from a life, may bee inferred the being of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6953:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>liuing things, Minerals, Hearbs, and Plants: So as, hither may be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> brought vp at the feete of the learned Hebrewe <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel,</hi> which he ſpake to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers of <hi>Athens, God himſelfe giueth life &amp; breath to al, euery where, for in him we liue and moue, and haue our being, as certaine of your owne Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets haue ſaid.</hi> For wee are alſo his offſpring; as that of the Poët, <hi>Chara Deûm ſoboles, magnum Iouis incrementu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Gods deareſt off-ſpring, mightie loues increaſe.</p>
               <p>And that of the Chriſtian Poët, who (as himſelfe affirmeth) wrote this, and much more after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Heathen:
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Vita est duplex, (ne tu ſis neſcius:) vna</l>
                     <l>Corporis, hanc ſequitur ſtultoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maxima turba,</l>
                     <l>Vulgus iners, Plebs inſipiens, quae nil ſapit altum,</l>
                     <l>Egregiúm<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, ignaua, colens pro Numine ventre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</l>
                     <l>Haec pecudum propria eſt, propria eſt haec vita fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum.</l>
                     <l>Altera verò Animi, Dijs conuenit, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Deorum</l>
                     <l>Nobilibus pueris, qui ob facta ingentia poſſunt</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6953:12"/>
                     <l> Verè homines, &amp; ſemidei, heroëſque vocari.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>I would not, but thou ſhouldeſt knowe</l>
                     <l>That liuing is twofold,</l>
                     <l>One, men of fleſh, a flocke of fooles</l>
                     <l>In greateſt price done holde,</l>
                     <l>The lazie ſcumme, and ideot ſort,</l>
                     <l>Which ſauour no-thing hie,</l>
                     <l>No-thing of worth, but doo their paunch</l>
                     <l>Adore as Deïtie:</l>
                     <l>This life belongeth to the tame</l>
                     <l>And to the ſauage beaſt.</l>
                     <l>That other life (yet) of the minde,</l>
                     <l>The Gods haue in requeſt,</l>
                     <l>And all their noble progenie,</l>
                     <l>Who for their great deſarts</l>
                     <l>Are termed men indeed, halfe-gods.</l>
                     <l>And men of mounting harts.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now, inaſmuch as in this word are the fiue vowels, which make all words; we may note, that we ought to ſpeake no word, but to haue in remembrance our God.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, from the two Aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, we may note; that we ought not ſo much as to breathe, but alſo to think of God, in whom we haue our life and breathing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6953:13"/>
               <head>Of the agreements of the Creatures with themſelues, and with the Creator.</head>
               <p>AS a man cannot <hi>Speake,</hi> but <hi>Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> nor breathe, but <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing;</hi> nor liue, but <hi>Being:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <label>Man, Angel: Man, Beaſt,</label>
                     <item>Homo, Angelus: Homo, Brutum.</item>
                     <label>Man, Beaſt, Liuing thing.</label>
                     <item>Homo, Brutum, Vegetans.</item>
                     <label>Creator, Creature.</label>
                     <item>Creator, Creatura.</item>
                  </list> ſo can the Creature, nor Speake, Breathe, Liue, nor Bee, but in God; in whoſe name, are the life of Speach, Breathing, Life, and Being.</p>
               <p>So then, Vegetant things agree with things Brute in life; Vegetant and Brute things agree with man in Life and Senſe: Man agreeth with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6953:13"/>Angells in Vnderſtanding, with an Heathen in Reaſon, with a bare Profeſſor in the knowledge of the word, with a true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in faith, which is of the word, which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth Chriſt, <hi>Immanuel,</hi> with vs GOD: who is <hi>Michael,</hi> one with God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Ends of the Creatures ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to themſelues, and how God is ſaid to be our End.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe that the End of a Beaſts life is to prouide for lïfe: So, or one Beaſt is for food to another, or els Herbes are for foode to ſome Beaſts: So ſaith the Poët:
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Torua Leaena Lupu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſequitur Lupus ipſe capella<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                     <l>Florentem citaſum ſequitur laſcina capella.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>The cruell Lyoneſſe laies waite</l>
                     <l>To take the Wolfe for pray:</l>
                     <l>The Wolfe he ſeekes the tender Kid,</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6953:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l> The Kid in wanton play</l>
                     <l>Doth crop the flowring three-leau'd graſſe.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But both Beaſts &amp; Herbes haue their Ends, or to giue food or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to Man, of whom the Angells haue their end in their Miniſterie, and God is the End of all.</p>
               <p>Againe, after another manner, according to this Figure, Man is both waies, vpward &amp; downward, not only the End of the other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but alſo his owne Ende, as to whoſe vſe, not onely are the other creatures, but alſo Man himſelfe is the Ende of Man, according to a twofold diuerſitie of vſe in ſenſe and in Reaſon. Vnder the firſt, which belongeth vnto Senſe, are contained all dueties of Mutuall loue, and the vnderſtanding of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things. From the ſecond vſe, which is of Reaſon, whereby wee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6953:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>know that we doo know ſo much as we knowe, and for to get the knowledge of our ſelues and our Powers, wee doo exerciſe our ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, aſwell as to the knowledge of other Creatures, by ſuch painfull experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce getting knowledge, how to communicate to common vſe the fruites of our knowledge, for common eaſe in things doubtfull or queſtionable by Arte, which is made of Acts chiefly, becauſe that To doo, is the end of Man, and the end of the whole Creature. Now, from the End are conſidered the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cauſes, of the Efficient, and of the matter, of the Perſon &amp; Thing, and of the Forme, about which are al other places of Logique: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Maſter <hi>Ramus</hi> ſaid well,
<q xml:lang="lat">Foelix qui potuit rerum cognoſcere cauſas.</q>
                  <q>O happie man, who can diſcerne the cauſes of</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6953:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> But with a further entendment may it be ſaid:
<q xml:lang="lat">Foelix qui potuit rerum cognoſcere fines.</q>
                  <q>O happie man, who can diſcerne the ſpeciall ends of things.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Arte is the mother of Science, which is had in a threefold diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, according to the foreſaid know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, or of Nature, or of Senſe, or of Reaſon, and is therfore called or Naturall, or Rationall, or Morall.</p>
               <p>With ſome cauſe therfore, was that Speach <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>know thy ſelfe,</hi> ſaide among the Heathen, to haue come from Heauen. For, a Man cannot fully knowe himſelfe, but he ſhall be drawne to conſider the whole Nature: by which word of Nature, I vnderſtand, not onely the powers and naked properties of Man, and other Creatures, but alſo what Acts ſoeuer are by Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by force of Reaſon. For
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6953:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>well ſaith the learned Scot, <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm aliud Natura, aliud Sapientia dicit. Nature and Arte neuer ſpeake diuers things.</hi> And another learned man, <hi>Naturam inueſtigantibus, inueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganda ſunt, tàm, quae quoquo modo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitantur, quàm quae ſuo ſunt robore. They, who ſeeke for an exquiſite know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Nature, muſt aſwell regard what effects doo accompany it, as what naturall faculties it hath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Concluſion, Man is the End of the Creation; and to doo is the End of Man vpon himſelfe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures. Chriſt is the End of Man, whom wee learne out of the word of GOD, vnto which he is <hi>Yea, and Amen:</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paule, GOD hath opened vnto vs the miſterie of his will, according to his good pleaſure, which he had purpoſed in himſelfe, That in the diſpenſation of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6953:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>the fulnes of the times, he might gather together in one all things in Chriſt, both which are in heauen, and which are in earth in him.</hi> God is the higheſt, and in reſpect only Cauſe, or End of al, who worketh all things after the good councell of his owne will.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6953:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
